Guide to the Irving Weissman Papers ALBA.165
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irving Weissman Papers
1937-1998, (Bulk 1977-1996)
bulk
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weissman, Irving, 1913-1998
ALBA.165
3 Linear Feet (4 boxes)
Irving Weissman (1913-1998) was a labor activist and a member of the Young Communist League before he went to fight in the Spanish Civil War. In Spain he trained and fought with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion. Weissman also fought with the United States Army in World War II. Weissman’s work as an organizer for the Communist Party in the late 1940s led him to be charged and tried under the Smith Act for conspiring to advocate the overthrow of the U.S. government; the charges were eventually dismissed. Later in life, Weissman was an active member of the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and was editor of their newsletter, The Volunteer, for several years. This collection includes correspondence written by Weissman while in Spain and documents related to his participation in the Spanish Civil War and World War II. It also contains extensive subject files related to VALB activities, especially in the 1970s and 1980s, and to Weissman's writings
Custodial History
One box of the Irving Weissman Papers was donated by Irving Weissman to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, then held at Brandeis University, in 1994. This material was transferred to the Tamiment Library, with the original acquisition of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections in January 2001. At that time a small Tamiment collection of Weissman material (Tam #226), comprised of itmes apparently donated by Weissman himself and material donated by Bolerium Books in 2000, was merged with the ALBA collection. In July of 2005, draft chapters of an autobiographical novel and other notes and manuscirpt fragments were donated by Robert Snyder and added to the collection. The accession NPA 2000.288 was added to this collection in 2015.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Irving Weissman (1913-1998) grew up in a Polish-Jewish immigrant family in New York City. In the early 1930s Weissman attended City College of New York for one year studying English literature and history. He quit school to work in a factory and help support his family. Weissman was a member of the Young Communist League and was active in the Fur and Leather Workers and the United Electrical Workers Unions. He participated in actions of unemployed and laid-off workers during the Depression. Weissman eventually got a Works Progress Administration (WPA) job teaching English to recent immigrants. He left this job to go to fight in the Spanish Civil War in 1937.
Weissman departed for Spain on the SS American Importer on May 8, 1937. In Spain, he trained with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion and went into action with that Battalion on the Aragon front and at Fuentes de Ebro in September and October 1937. Weissman fell ill at the end of October and was sent to Barcelona with a delegation of the 15th International Brigade where he performed guard duties while he recovered. He rejoined the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion in December 1937. Weissman left Spain on December 15, 1938.
Upon his return to the United States Weissman worked as a ship's fitter in Hoboken, New Jersey. He was a member of the Industrial Union of Marine and Shipbuilding Workers of America, Local 15 and was elected to the Union's grievance committee. Weissman served in the United States Army from 1942 to 1945. During World War II he fought in campaigns in North Africa, Italy, France, Belgium, and Germany. When he returned to the United States he accepted an assignment from the Communist Party--of which he was then a member--to be an organizer, first in western New York State, then in West Virginia.
In 1951 Weissman was arrested along with five other veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and Communist Party members and charged, under the Smith Act, with conspiring to advocate the overthrow of the United States government. Weissman was sentenced to five years in prison but the case was appealed. In 1956 the Supreme Court ruled that the case be retried and the new prosecutor's motion to dismiss the case was granted. In the intervening years Weissman had spent several months in jail while bail was raised and had served time for contempt of court for refusing to give names of Communist Party members on the witness stand. In the late 1950s Weissman left the Communist Party.
Weissman worked in building construction in New York from 1953 until his retirement in 1978. Throughout this time and for the rest of his life he was active in neighborhood politics and with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB). Weissman headed a campaign to secure pension rights for Polish-Jewish veterans of the Botwin Company, some of whom were charging the Polish authorities with anti-Semitism. He was also editor of The Volunteer for several years during the 1980s. When his wife Freda died in the early 1990s Weissman moved from New York to San Francisco to be near his daughters and grandchildren. He remained active with VALB on the west coast, helping to raise funds for a monument in Seattle. Irving Weissman died of congestive heart failure on December 20, 1998.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Spanish Civil War and World War II Era, 1937-1946. The bulk of this series consists of correspondence written by Irving Weissman to his sister Sara and his parents from Spain between May 1937 and October 1938. Two letters are written in Yiddish, using the Roman alphabet. Weissman wrote long, detailed letters about his journey to Spain, the landscape, his training, life in the barracks, and his experiences on the fronts. The economic hardships that his family was facing at home in the United States are discussed as well as his parents' worries for their son's safety. Weissman's letters provide evidence of his political convictions as well as how his point of view evolved as a result of experiencing war first hand. As well as writing to his family, Weissman wrote to friends and political comrades and he maintained contact with an imprisoned Spanish comrade, Jose Ferando Ventura, after returning to the United States. This series contains documents related to the Spanish Civil War and to Weissman's service in the United States Army during World War II, most notably, a diary he kept while serving in Europe. The series also contains union cards and documents that reveal some of Weissman's activities and areas of employment in the years between the two wars.
Series II, Subject Files, 1951-1996 (bulk 1977-1996). This series consists of correspondence, essays and articles, and other documents related to Weissman's activities with the Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB) and his position as editor of their newsletter, The Volunteer. Correspondence in this series is mostly incoming and third party correspondence sent or forwarded to Weissman by other VALB members. VALB members represented in this collection include Theodore (Ted) Cogswell, Carl Geiser, Ben Iceland, Edward Lending, Abe Osheroff, Abe Smorodin, Morris Stamm, and Robert Steck. The series contains letters and writings by these and other veterans. This series also contains records relating to VALB activities, particularly those in New York but also regional and national efforts. Included in the VALB files are a copy of the VALB and American Medical Bureau Names List compiled by Ted Cogswell, records related to some of the organization's bureaus and commissions, and documents on VALB's campaign to send aid to the Sandinistas in Nicaragua. Weissman's work on behalf of Polish-Jewish Spanish Civil War veterans is well documented in this series. Finally, the series contains essays, articles, and book reviews written by Weissman.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 2 series:
Missing Title
I, Spanish Civil War and World War II Era, 1937-1946
II, Subject Files, 1951-1996 (bulk 1977-1998)
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Separated Material
Photographs from the Irving Weissman Papers have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Songs and music.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Campaigns.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Drafts (documents); Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Periodicals.; Spain |x History |y Civil War, 1936-1939 |v Sources.; Articles.; Biography files.; Correspondence.; Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives; Cogswell, Theodore R.; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Bay Area Post; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade; Lending, Edward Isaac, 1912-2003; Geiser, Carl; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade. Historical Commission; Smorodin, Abe.; Osheroff, Abe.; Steck, Robert; Stamm, Morris.; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion; Iceland, Benjamin, 1910-1990
- Series I: Spanish Civil War and World War II Era
  - Friends of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade to Weissman Family, Dec 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rissane, Tomas to Irving Weissman, Jun 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ventura, Jose Ferrando to Irving Weissman, Jul 1939-Aug 1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Weissman, Irving to Saul Cassim, undated, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Weissman, Irving to Unidentified Correspondents, Aug 1937, Mar 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Weissman, Irving to Unidentified Correspondents: Comrades, undated, [May] 1937-Jun-37 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Weissman, Irving to Unidentified Correspondent: Edith, May 1937-Oct 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Weissman, Irving to Unidentified Correspondents: Letter Fragments, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Weissman, Irving to Sara Weissman and Family, ca.May 1937-Aug 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Weissman, Irving to Sara Weissman and Family, Sep 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Weissman, Irving to Sara Weissman and Family, Dec 1937-Feb 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Weissman, Irving to Sara Weissman and Family, Mar 1938-Oct 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Weissman, Sara to Irving Weissman, Nov [1938] (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Documents (Spain), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - "Good Luck Guys" Re: Moe Fishman, etc., [1937-1938] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lincoln Battalion: Shipboard Concert ("Ansonia"), 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Songs, [1937-1938] (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Union Cards and Documents, 1939-1945 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Delegate Badge, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - World War II Correspondence: Postcard to IW from Moses Kohl, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - World War II Era Diary, ca.1943 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - World War II: Order to Report for Induction, Oct 1942 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - "Weissman-Spanish Civil War/John Jay College of Criminal Justice Thematic Studies Department", Mar 1, 1977; 1 Reels 1 1/2 inch open reel video tape (Box 4)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Researchers interested in using audiovisual materials that have not been digitized (films, cassette tapes, VHS tapes, et cetera) must request an access copy. Researchers may view an item’s original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that already have already been digitized are noted in the collection’s finding aid and can be requested in our reading room; materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. These requests are free of charge and can be made in anticipation of your visit. The process typically takes four to six weeks. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu.
  - "Ay, Carmela!", undated; 1 videocassette 1 VHS tape (Box 4)
- Series II: Subject Files
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA), undated, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives: High School Curriculum, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Albertini, Henry: Critique of the Popular Front in Spain (L. Chodorow Transcription and Cover Letter), 1939, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - American Medical Bureau: Randall Smith Questionnaire, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Aub, Max: Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bailey, William (Bill), undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Baley, Barney: "Pearl and Barney Baley Go to Spain", ca.1979 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bessie, Alvah: In Memoriam, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Brandt, Joseph: "Fighting for Destruction of Fascism: World War II", undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Brown, Archie, Re: Susman's "Spain's Changing Face", Jun 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Campaign for Peace and Democracy East and West, undated, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Canadian Volunteers--Spain 1936-1939, W. Beeching: Smorodin Review, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Carrillo, Santiago, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Carrillo, Santiago: Yale Controversy, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Casals, Pablo: Letter to Maury Colow, Jun 4, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 36A)
  - Causes: Miscellaneous, Undated 1973-1987 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Chagall, Marc: Letter in Freiheit, Dec 1975 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Chase, Homer, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - China: Report by Communist Party of Spain Delegation, ca.1971 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings: Miscellaneous, Undated 1978-1988 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Cogswell, Theodore, 1984-1986 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Colodny, Robert: Review of Nelson and Hendricks: Madrid 1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Colodny, Robert: Vittorio Vidali (Carlos Contreras) Essay, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Communism: Klehr-Haynes Book, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Cook, Geraldo: In Memoriam, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - correspondence: Cards, Greeting and Post, Undated 1976-1978 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence: General, Undated; 1972-1979 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence: General, Undated 1980-1992 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence: Weissman, Irving to Freda, [?1976] (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Cuba: Account of Visit (unsigned fragment), undated (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Czechoslovakian Volunteers, undated, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Dean, Jeannette, Jan 1977 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Doyle, Joe: "The American Woman Pickets", Apr 1984-May 1984 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Felsen, Milt, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Filipino Volunteers, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Fishman, Moe, undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Franco and the Jews (from Morris Schappes), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Geiser, Carl, undated, 1977-1992 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Goldring, Benjamin, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Goldstein, Benjamin (Butch), undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Gonshak, Sam, Apr 1983 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Grant, Walter: In Memoriam, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Gruen, Arno: "On Abstraction: The Reduction and Destruction of Human Experience", 1978 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Hargrave, Roger, Feb 1980-Jun 1980 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Harriman, Manny, 1977-1986 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Hemingway, Ernest, ca.1994 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Henkine, Kirill (Soviet Jewish Veteran), ca. 1973 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Hitler-Stalin Pact, Aug 1979 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Ibarruri, Dolores, undated (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Iceland, Ben, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Iceland, Ben and Tom Lloyd, Jul 1986 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Jackson, Gabriel, undated, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Jewish Currents, undated, 1984, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Jewish Welfare Association, 1976; 1978 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Journals and Notes, undated (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Keith, Charles, Mar 1978 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Kerin, Armand, undated (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Knox, Bernard, 1983, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Kramer, Jacob, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Kugler, Israel: Irving Weissman's Response to, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Lamb, Leonard, 1949, 1979, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Landis, Arthur, Jul 1978 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory Protest, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Lending, Edward, 1977-1995 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Levine, Sidney, Jan 1980 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Loach, Ken: "Land and Freedom", 1995 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Lossowski, Vincent, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - MacLeod, Don, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Malefakis, Edward: "Spain and its Francoist Heritage", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Marchais, George: Excerpt from "Socialism for France", Feb 1976 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Marion, George: Correspondence from Spain (photocopies), undated, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Martin, Fredericka, 1973-1981 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Martin, Hew, Nov 1977 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Miller, David M., 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Moreno, Idolino Sanchez, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Mount Holyoke College, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - National Public Radio: "All Things Considered" Transcript, Jul 1993 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Nelson, Steve, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Nicaragua, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Notes: Miscellaneous, Undated (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Novick, Paul: "The Fight against Left Sectarianism", Aug 1977 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Nusser, Charles, 1983-1985 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - O'Casey, Sean, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - O'Riordan, Manus, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Osheroff, Abe, 1970s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - O'Toole, Lawrence, Nov 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Our Fight: Writings by Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade," ed. Alvah Bessie and Albert Prago, 1984-1987 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Page, Tom: In Memoriam, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Petition against Military Spending, Jul 1976 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Picket, Morris, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Polish-Jewish Veterans: Controversy, 1972-1992 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Polish-Jewish Veterans Controversy: Correspondence, 1970-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Polish-Jewish Veterans Controversy: Correspondence, undated; 1980-1992 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Polish-Jewish Veterans Controversy: Documents (in Polish), 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Prago, Albert, undated, 1979-1991 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Reagan, Ronald: Remarks Re: Abraham Lincoln Brigade, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Reed, Robert, 1992-1995 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Robeson, Paul, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Rosen, Alex: In Memoriam, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rosenberg, Leo: "Sally and Jack--A Love Story", undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Rosenbergs: Commemoration, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Rossen, John, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Ryan, Frank, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Salzman, Salman J., undated, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Schindler, Harry, Apr 1984 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Schneider, Theodore: Controversy, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Segre, Sergio, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Smith Act Trial, 1951-1957 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Smith, Randall, undated, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Smorodin, Abe, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Snyder, Rob, 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Soviet Yiddish Writers, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Spain: Clippings, 1973-1984 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Spain: History, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Spain: Politics, 1979-1983 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Spanish Citizenship: Weissman Application, 1995-1996 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Spanish Civil War: Clippings, undated; 1971-1984 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Spanish Civil War: Fifty Years of Myth and Memory": Conference Report, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Spanish Refugee Aid, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Stamm, Morris, undated, 1984-1989 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Steck, Robert, undated, 1979-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Steve Nelson: American Radical: Debate and Review, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Stone, Oliver, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Susman, William, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Tisa, John, 1977; 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Tisa, John: Controversy Re: Levenson Review, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - United States Congress: Bill to Provide Lincoln Brigade Veterans Benefits, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade and American Medical Bureau Names List (Cogswell), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade (VALB): Bay Area Post, 1979-1984 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - VALB: Constitution, undated, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - VALB: Controversies, undated, 1976-1992 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - VALB: General, 1976-1992 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - VALB: Historical Commission, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - VALB: Osheroff-Muller Controversy, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - VALB: Reunion in Italy, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - VALB: Rosenstein Controversy, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - VALB: Speakers Bureau, Undated; 1972-1980 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - VALB: Stuyvesant Memorial, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - VALB: Susman Resignation from Board, 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Volunteer: Controversies, 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Volunteer: Correspondence, 1984-1992 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Volunteer: General, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Volunteer: Prago-Lending Controversy, undated, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Wasserman, Suzanne: "Memories of McCarthyism…" (Play), 1983 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Weissman, Ann: School Report, Jun 1952 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Weissman, Freda, undated, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Weissman, Irving: Biographical, undated, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Weissman, Stephanie, 1973, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Wellman, Saul, 1973, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Wolff, Milton, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Writings: "Battlefield Rome", Undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Writings: Correspondence with Publishers, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Writings: "How It Was Then" ( New Leader with William Herrick Essay), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Writings: Miscellaneous, undated, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Writings: "The Nature of Beauty", Undated (Box 2, Folder 74)
  - Writings: Novel, chapter "1945", Undated (Box 2, Folder 75)
  - Writings: Novel, chapter "Busy Morning", Undated; 1998 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Writings: Novel, Chapter "Home", Undated (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Writings: Novel, chapter "Lunch with Lamonica", Undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Writings: Novel, Fragment, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Writings: Novel, Fragments, Undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Writings: Novel, Fragments and Notes, Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Writings: Personal, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Writings: "The Return", Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Writings: Review, Blood of Spain: An Oral History of the Spanish Civil War, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Writings: Review, The Forgotten War, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Writings: Review, A Long View from the Left, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Writings: Reviews, drafts, Undated; 1987 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Writings: "Wild Horses of Anzio", 1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)